Mother,
Madre.
you're airing out the books again.
¿Está secando los libros otra vez?
This time, I'm not airing out the books.
Esta vez no estoy secando los libros,
In fact, I'm taking all of them
sino que
away.
me los llevo todos.
Are you leaving, Mother?
Madre, ¿se va a ir?
What makes you say that?
¿Cómo lo sabes?
You love books as much as your life.
Madre, quiere los libros más que a su vida.
If the books are leaving,
Si los libros se van,
then you must be leaving too.
seguro que usted también se irá.
You're very smart, Ziqi.
Ziqi, eres muy inteligente.
But don't you worry.
Pero no te preocupes, Ziqi.
I'm just moving to another place.
Solo voy a mudarme a otro lugar.
I'll still come back from time to time
Puedo volver de vez en cuando
to check your homework.
a revisar tus deberes.
Do you see that box? Your homework's in it.
Mira esa caja, ahí tienes tus tareas.
Ziqi, go back and get changed now.
Ziqi, ve a cambiarte rápido.
You're covered in sweat. Let's go.
Estás todo sudado. Vamos.
So you've set a day?
¿Ya se fijó la fecha?
His Highness said
El heredero ha dicho que
this courtyard would be reserved for me.
este patio se quedará para mí.
I will still be Ziqi's teacher,
Seguiré siendo la maestra de Ziqi
and a member of the household.
y seguiré siendo parte de la mansión.
I didn't expect
Nunca pensé que
this day to arrive eventually.
llegaría este día.
But I think
Yo, en cambio, siento
it's a good thing that this day came.
alivio de haber llegado a este día.
I remember the day
Recuerdo aquel día
when I picked you up from the He Mansion
que fui a la mansión He a buscarte en nombre de Wuyi,
and completed
para completar
the wedding with you on Wuyi's behalf.
la ceremonia por él.
At that time, I thought,
En ese momento pensé que
my brother was lucky
mi hermano tenía suerte
to marry such a girl as the Heir's Consort.
de casarse con una mujer como tú.
Anmin...
Yao.
I know
Sé que
between you and Wuyi,
entre tú y Wuyi
there is trust,
hay confianza
but never love.
pero no afecto.
This is his loss.
Él no tiene la suerte.
These few books
Estos libros
are about river management.
son sobre el control de ríos,
There are also some medical books.
y algunos de medicina.
I think they might be of help to you.
Creo que te serán útiles.
Yuanji, if I...
Yuanji, si yo...
If I were not Wuyi's brother,
Si yo no fuera el hermano de Wuyi…
-I... -Brother.
- Yao. - Yo...
I do not fear gossip.
Yo no temo lo que digan los demás.
However,
Pero
I've always seen you as a brother figure.
siempre te he considerado mi hermano.
I deem it as a blessing for me
Poder casarme en la familia Xiao
to marry into the Xiao family,
y tenerlos como familia,
to become part of the household,
apoyándonos mutuamente,
and to support each other here.
es una bendición para mí.
You are always so clever,
Siempre eres tan inteligente.
not leaving me a glimmer of hope.
No dejas ni un resquicio a la esperanza.
Never mind.
Está bien.
Upon stepping out of this door,
Al salir de esta puerta,
you'll be embraced by the vast world.
el mundo será infinito.
I wish you all the best, and may all your dreams
Que tengas todo lo que deseas
come true.
y que tus sueños se cumplan.
[Key to the Phoenix Heart]
[Llave del Corazón del Fénix]
[Episode 21]
[Episodio 21]
[Northern Qin]
[Beiqin]
Quick!
¡Rápido!
Keep moving!
¡Váyanse!
Get up. Get up now!
¡Levántate, levántate!
Hold on!
¡Alto!
Your Highness.
Rey Águila.
Princess Pingning?
¿Vizcondesa Pingning?
What a coincidence.
Qué casualidad.
It's not.
No es casualidad.
I came specifically to find you.
He venido a buscarte.
Get a move on!
Rápido.
Go!
¡Vamos!
Quick!
¡Rápido!
Didn't you say...
Antes dijiste que...
If you change your mind one day,
Si algún día cambias de opinión,
come to Northern Qin to find me.
ven a Beiqin a buscarme.
My Eagle King's Mansion
La puerta de mi mansión
will always open its doors for you!
siempre estará abierta para ti.
Now, I am here.
Ahora que estoy aquí.
Are you regretting it?
¿Te arrepientes?
A beauty throws herself into my arms.
Una bella mujer se entrega,
How could I refuse?
¿cómo me atrevería a rechazarla?
Pretty though this flower is,
Pero aunque la flor es hermosa,
I am not sure
no sé
if it is toxic.
si es venenosa.
I killed Xie Jiayu's mother,
Maté a la madre de Xie Jiayu,
namely Princess Yunzhao.
la condesa Yun Zhao.
I just escaped from the clutches of Xiao Wuyi
He escapado de las manos
and Xie Jiayu.
de Xiao Wuyi y Xie Jiayu.
If I go back to Ye,
Si vuelvo a Ye,
all that awaits me is death.
solo me espera la muerte.
I have no home to go to now.
Ya no tengo hogar.
Xiao Wuyi is a domineering dictator.
Xiao Wuyi es tiránico y arbitrario.
My brother simply
Mi hermano
cannot put up a fight against him.
no puede enfrentarlo.
But I believe that one day,
Pero creo que algún día
my brother will definitely go to war with him
mi hermano se enfrentará a él
and have a final showdown.
en batalla.
On this matter,
En este asunto,
I assume you and my brother share the same goal.
creo que usted y mi hermano tienen el mismo objetivo.
I can be
Puedo ser
a bridge between the two of you.
el puente entre ustedes dos.
You...
Tú...
Let go of...
Suéltame...
Alright. This is enough!
Ya, ya, ya.
Already packed everything up?
¿Terminaste tan rápido?
Mother.
Madre.
Yuanji, over all these years,
Yuanji, todos estos años,
in the huge Prince Jing'an's Mansion,
en esta enorme Mansión del Rey Jing'an,
you've actually been the one keeping me company.
has sido tú quien me ha acompañado.
It's a shame
Lástima que
that we are not destined to be in-laws.
no tengamos la fortuna de ser suegra y nuera.
Wuyi aside,
No mencionemos a Wuyi.
in fact,
Pero
Anmin...
en cuanto a Anmin…
Mother.
Madre,
I feel guilty about someone,
en mi corazón tengo una deuda con alguien
and can never stop feeling so.
que no puedo olvidar.
My heart is burdened.
Tengo una preocupación.
Fine, forget it.
Está bien.
The Xiao family doesn't have the luck to keep you around.
Es que nuestra familia Xiao no ha tenido esa suerte.
Yuanji, you're about to return home after the divorce
Yuanji, esta vez que te divorcias y vuelves a casa,
to solve the long-standing problems in the He family.
tendrás que arreglar los problemas de la familia He.
Once your family agrees with the reform,
Una vez que la familia He apoye las reformas,
it will surely be attacked by other noble families.
será atacada por las otras familias nobles.
A lot of difficulties are lying ahead of you.
Te esperan muchas dificultades.
If you really can't cope,
Si tienes problemas,
just come back to us.
vuelve aquí.
Jinyi Courtyard
Este Jardín Jinyi
will still be yours.
seguirá siendo tuyo.
Prince Jing'an's Mansion
La Mansión del Rey Jing'an
will always be your home.
será siempre tu hogar.
Mother...
Madre.
Yuanji,
Yuanji,
for so many years,
todos estos años
I have always wanted a daughter.
he querido tener una hija,
It's a pity that I can't have one.
pero no he tenido suerte.
How about I take you as my goddaughter?
¿Qué te parece si te tomo como hija adoptiva?
From now on, we will address each other as mother and daughter.
De ahora en adelante, nos llamaremos madre e hija,
And you will still be Ziqi's teacher.
y seguirás siendo la maestra de Ziqi.
What do you think?
¿Qué te parece?
If you deem me worthy,
Madre, si me quiere,
I'm more than willing to do so.
yo, Yuanji, acepto con gusto.
These few years I spent in Prince Jing'an's Mansion
Estos años en la Mansión del Rey Jing'an
were the most free
han sido los más libres
and unrestrained days of my life.
y felices de mi vida.
I consider myself extremely fortunate.
Soy muy afortunada.
Please get up.
Levántate.
Does Yuanji not plan
¿Yuanji
to tell Liu Zhaolin about his origins?
no piensa contarle a Liu Zhaolin su verdadera identidad?
Empress Dowager He already found an excuse
La familia Pei fue ejecutada
to execute the entire Pei family.
por la Emperatriz Suprema con cualquier excusa.
Suppose Liu Zhaolin is reminded
Si Liu Zhaolin recuerda
of himself being Pei Runheng
que él es Pei Runheng,
right now, when He Yuanji is about to take charge of the He family,
y He Yuanji ahora dirige la familia He,
he will come to realize
en realidad,
that she is actually an enemy of his.
también será enemigo de Liu Zhaolin.
Then how should
Entre ellos dos,
the two of them face each other?
¿cómo podrán enfrentarse el uno al otro?
Now, the Cui Family Case has been tried
Los resultados del juicio del caso de la familia Cui,
and reviewed.
ya salieron.
Conclusive evidence confirms
La familia Cui explotó minas ilegales
that the Cui family illegally mined
y maltrató a mujeres.
and brutalized women.
Las pruebas son concluyentes.
However, Cui Jun already died.
Sin embargo, Cui Jun ya murió.
Cui Lingyi and Cui Shao'an
Cui Lingyi y Cui Shao'an
stopped Cui Jun from destroying the fields
detuvieron juntos a Cui Jun de destruir los campos
so as to help the women escape.
y ayudaron a las mujeres a escapar.
Their merits offset their faults.
Sus méritos y culpas se compensan.
In the end, their property was confiscated,
Finalmente, se confiscan sus bienes
and Cui Shao'an was reduced to a commoner.
y Cui Shao'an es reducido a plebeyo.
There's still mercy left in Mao.
Mao sigue siendo de buen corazón.
Do you no longer blame him
¿Ya no le guardas rencor
for what Li Lejun did?
por lo de Li Lejun?
You told me to handle it myself, didn't you?
¿No me dijiste que lo decidiera yo misma?
This matter is over now.
Eso ya está cerrado.
Actually, I have cracked the secret
En realidad, ya he descifrado el secreto
within the Phoenix Heart Tokens.
de la llave del corazón del fénix.
Whether they exist or not no longer matters now.
Tenerla o no no es tan importante.
Look.
Mira.
These three spots on the map
Estos tres puntos brillantes en el mapa
are the locations of mineral deposits.
son donde están los yacimientos minerales.
This is the map my master drew
Este es el mapa topográfico que mi maestro dibujó
after traveling all over Ye.
recorriendo todo Ye antes de morir.
Look at these three places here.
Mira estos tres lugares en el mapa.
They match the three spots
¿No se parecen mucho a los tres puntos
on the tokens, don't they?
de la llave del corazón del fénix?
I've asked Ye Xing to bring back
Envié a Ye Xing a esos lugares
water and soil from these places.
para que trajera muestras de agua y tierra,
Then we'll know if there are minerals hidden there.
así podremos saber si hay minerales.
Ye Xing?
¿Ye Xing?
He's that Shadow Envoy.
Es ese Enviado de la Sombra.
I gave him a name.
Yo le puse el nombre.
I didn't mean to let him stay at first.
No quería quedármelo,
But he said the mission of a Shadow Envoy
pero dijo que la misión de los Enviados de la Sombra
is to protect the royal family.
es proteger a la familia real.
With Princess Yunzhao's passing,
Como la condesa ha muerto,
he was supposed to take his own life.
él debería haberse suicidado.
If I refused to keep him around,
Si no me lo quedaba,
he would have to die.
solo le quedaba morir.
That was really scary.
Eso es demasiado aterrador.
So I had to let him stick around.
Así que no tuve más remedio que quedármelo
I also gave him a name.
y darle un nombre.
I'd hate for him
No quiero
to end up like his brother.
que termine como su hermano.
Is it a rule for all Shadow Envoys
¿Las reglas de los Enviados de la Sombra
serving the royalty?
de la familia imperial son todas así?
That is, envoys have to be buried with their dead masters.
¿Cuando el señor muere, ellos deben morir con él?
Then what about your previous...
¿Y los que tenías antes…?
They've been trained this way since they were little.
Han sido entrenados así desde pequeños.
They consider such conduct an honor.
Lo consideran un honor.
It cannot be changed overnight.
No se puede cambiar de la noche a la mañana.
Fine.
Está bien.
Although Empress Wenxi was your mother,
Aunque la emperatriz Wenxi era tu madre
and Emperor Wenxi your father,
y el emperador Wenxi era tu padre,
I have to say they did
debo decir
resort to terrifying methods.
que sus métodos eran bastante aterradores.
They were not much better than Cui Jun.
No mucho mejores que los de Cui Jun.
So, it is actually good for you to forsake the post
Así que mejor que no seas
of Crown Prince Wenxi.
el Príncipe Heredero Wenxi.
Did you really revive him?
¿De verdad lo salvaste?
Yes, he's also from the Beifu Army.
Él también es del ejército de Beifu.
Last year, he suffered serious head trauma,
El año pasado recibió un golpe fuerte en la cabeza
resulting in blood stasis.
y le quedó un coágulo de sangre.
His case was severer than yours.
Pero su caso era peor que el tuyo.
He went blind immediately.
Se quedó ciego de inmediato.
For the past year,
Durante este año,
I have been treating him.
lo he estado tratando.
Having a strong will to live,
Él también quería vivir.
he boldly tried every treatment
Se atrevía a probar cualquier método
and medicine available.
y a tomar cualquier medicina.
Now, I've finally found a way
Por fin encontré
to clear blood stasis.
la manera de eliminar el coágulo.
His vision is restored as we speak.
Ahora ha recuperado la vista.
With proper care,
Si se cuida bien,
I believe he'll live for as long as any other healthy man.
creo que puede vivir tanto como una persona normal.
What's the way?
¿Qué método?
Acupuncture, plus an incision into the skull.
Acupuntura y trepanación.
How many patients have you treated this way?
¿Cuántos pacientes has tratado así?
Three.
Tres.
And only this one survived, right?
Solo ha sobrevivido uno, ¿verdad?
What about the other two?
¿Y los otros dos?
Are they dead or paralyzed?
¿Murieron o quedaron paralizados?
I went to great lengths
Encontrar un método
to finally find a way,
ya es difícil,
yet you're still being picky!
y encima te pones exigente.
You want to live, don't you?
¿No quieres vivir?
Now I've offered you a solution.
Ya te di el método.
If you refuse to try,
Si no quieres intentarlo,
then forget I ever said it.
olvida lo que dije.
I won't try it.
No lo intento.
Your condition isn't as serious as his.
Tu caso no es tan grave como el suyo.
The treatment won't be as risky.
El tratamiento no será tan arriesgado.
I can tell you for sure
Te lo aseguro,
that I'm more confident with your case.
contigo tengo más confianza.
Once cured, you won't
Si te curas,
have to worry about dying soon.
no tendrás riesgo de muerte prematura.
I can't afford to take
Aunque sea el riesgo más pequeño,
even the slightest risk.
no puedo apostar,
Neither can Beifu.
y Beifu tampoco.
Fine.
Bien.
Then just wait to go blind in three years
Entonces espera a quedarte ciego en tres años
and die in five.
y a morir en cinco.
I'm off to tell Jiayu about this.
Voy a decírselo a Jiayu.
I forbid you from doing so!
¡No vayas!
This is a military order.
Es una orden militar.
Jiayu doesn't know about your condition.
Jiayu no sabe de tu enfermedad.
She's even planning to travel all over Ye
Ella planea recorrer todo Ye
to restore the mineral map.
para restaurar el mapa de las minas.
Can you bear to see that happen?
¿La dejarías ir?
She's doing it for Princess Yunzhao,
Ella lo hace por la condesa,
and also for fulfilling
también por ella misma
her own wish of exploring the world.
para cumplir su sueño de viajar por todas partes.
There isn't much time left for you already.
Pero no les queda mucho tiempo,
You can...
pueden...
Why even wait?
¿Esperar a qué?
So she'll finally
¿Esperar a que yo muera
have freedom only after I die?
para darle libertad?
What if I'm in luck
¿Y si tengo suerte
and still alive five years later?
y no muero en cinco años?
How can I ask her to just stick around
¿Ella tendría que quedarse a mi lado todo el tiempo
and be with me the entire time?
cuidándome?
Xie Jiayu has her own path to tread.
Xie Jiayu tiene su propio camino.
Has it ever crossed your mind
¿Pero has pensado que
that Jiayu will figure out the truth eventually?
Jiayu se enterará de la verdad tarde o temprano?
What will she think then?
¿Qué pensará ella?
If your condition worsens faster than anticipated,
Si tu enfermedad empeora antes de tiempo
leaving you with less than three to five years,
y no llegas a los tres o cinco años,
she will hate you when she returns from her travels
y ella vuelve de su viaje y descubre que ya has muerto,
only to find you dead, won't she?
¿te odiará?
Right?
¿Cierto?
Xiao Wuyi.
Xiao Wuyi,
I was talking to you.
estoy hablando contigo.
Did you hear me?
¿Me escuchas?
What was it?
¿Qué?
I said,
Digo
Cangshan is very close to Beifu's Yunzhong Camp.
que la montaña Cang está cerca del campamento Yunzhong de Beifu.
Can I have a short stay there
Si paso por allí,
if I ever pass by?
¿puedo alojarme?
Of course.
Por supuesto.
You're now family with a member of the Beifu Army.
Ahora eres parte de la familia del ejército de Beifu.
Do remember to write to me.
No olvides escribirme.
You just focus on the Beifu Reform.
Ocúpate bien de la reforma de Beifu.
I'll go find you.
Yo también iré a buscarte.
It won't take much time to defeat Northern Qin, Xiao Wuyi.
Derrotar a Beiqin será rápido, Xiao Wuyi,
Trust me.
confía en mí.
I'll definitely find the mineral deposits
Definitivamente voy a encontrar
and produce caltrop fireballs
el yacimiento mineral para ti y mi maestro,
for you and my master.
y fabricaré la granada de fuego.
♪ Hear the heartbeat by my side ♪
♪ Escucha, el latido de mi corazón resuena en mis oídos ♪
♪ Like your rush of passion toward me ♪
♪ Tan apasionado como te precipitas hacia mí ♪
♪ A toast to our romantic encounter ♪
♪ Brindo por este instante pleno, sin traicionar nuestro pacto ♪
♪ I am here only for you ♪
♪ Solo por ti he llegado ♪
Having gained more and more along the journey,
En este viaje, los hallazgos son cada vez más numerosos.
♪ Even though I know tremendous danger lies ahead ♪
♪ Aunque bien sé que el camino está lleno de peligros. ♪
I've completed the structure of the caltrop fireball.
La estructura de la granada de fuego está casi lista.
The biggest problem now
El mayor problema ahora
♪ If you could fill the empty spaces in my memories ♪
♪ Si pudiera llenar los vacíos de mi memoria ♪
lies in the ore for making gunpowder.
es el mineral para la pólvora.
♪ Only you would stay with me ♪
♪ Solo tú estás conmigo ♪
♪ My heartbeat will never fade ♪
♪ Los latidos del corazón nunca se agotan ♪
♪ The wishes left unsaid ♪
♪ Los deseos que no te puedo decir ♪
♪ A love I can't let go ♪
♪ Un vínculo inquebrantable ♪
It's colder at night in Beifu than in Jiankang.
Las noches en Beifu son más frías que en Jiankang.
♪ A red thread woven by fate ♪
♪ El hilo rojo del destino ♪
What is Jiayu doing right now?
¿Qué estará haciendo Jiayu ahora?
♪ Love carries longing through time ♪
♪ El amor hará que el tiempo se intercambie por anhelo ♪
Has she reached Mount Cang yet?
¿Ya habrá llegado a la montaña Cang?
♪ To make it come true ♪
♪ Para cumplir ♪
How's the development of the caltrop fireball going?
¿Cómo va el desarrollo de la granada de fuego?
[Two years later, Lai Lake]
[Dos años después, Laihu]
Pass the ball to me!
Pateálo.
Over here!
Por acá.
It looks pretty nice.
Se ve bien.
What is this thing?
¿Qué es esto?
I've never seen it before.
Nunca lo había visto.
Keep it down. Miss Xie said
Baja la voz. La señorita Xie dijo
this was transformed from an immortal.
que lo hizo un espíritu inmortal.
If you get too loud
Si haces mucho ruido
and scare the immortal away,
y asustas al inmortal,
we won't have any grain to eat next year.
el año que viene no tendremos cosecha.
It has come to life! The wood is animated!
¡Vive, vive! ¡La madera se ha convertido en un duende!
There's water!
¡Llega el agua!
Water's flowing right out of it.
Sale directamente.
This is amazing.
¡Es increíble!
From now on, you can divert
De ahora en adelante no tendrán que cargar agua.
the mountain streams directly into the farmland
Podrán traer el agua del arroyo de la montaña
without fetching water on your own.
directamente a los campos.
Thank you, miss.
Muchas gracias, señorita.
Our husbands have all gone to build the canal.
Los hombres de la familia fueron a construir canales.
With this waterwheel,
Con esta noria,
we won't have to carry water from the mountain anymore.
ya no tendremos que subir a la montaña a buscar agua.
That's right.
Así es.
What is it now?
¿Y esto qué es?
The Miraculous Craft
En la Tienda Maravillosa
offers many more novel devices.
tenemos muchas cosas nuevas.
They are absolutely real
Todas son auténticas
and helpful to you.
y pueden ayudar a todos.
This device can plow over 20 mu a day,
Este artefacto puede arar más de veinte mu al día,
equaling three strong oxen.
equivalente a tres bueyes fuertes.
Three oxen?
¿Tres bueyes?
Sounds incredible.
¿Tan potente es?
The bamboo strips and palm leaves of this rain cape
Traté especialmente las tiras de bambú y las hojas de palma
have undergone special treatment.
de este impermeable.
I guarantee you won't get wet at all
Cuando llueva a cántaros, te lo pones
when you wear it in heavy rain.
y no te mojas ni una gota.
Top quality, fairly pricing.
Es de buena calidad, precio justo,
A genuine good deal.
totalmente auténtico.
-That impressive? -This is great.
¿Tan bueno es? ¡Qué bien!
How amazing.
¡Increíble!
Oh no, My Lady.
Se acabó, señorita.
Another explosion.
Explotó otra vez.
Why an explosion?
¿Cómo explotó?
Cui Shao'an!
¡Cui Shao'an!
Careful, ladies.
Tengan cuidado.
Cui Shao'an.
Cui Shao'an.
Did you... get hurt?
Esto... ¿Estás herido?
Don't overthink it.
No pienses mal.
She's just concerned about your safety.
Está preocupada por ti.
It seems this batch of ore
Parece que la pureza de este lote de minerales
is still not pure enough
aún no es suficiente.
to be used for caltrop fireballs.
No se puede usar para la granada de fuego.
It's fine.
No importa.
I'll go look for more.
Iré a buscar más.
Who would've known?
Quién lo diría.
The Mr. Cui who never did physical labor before
Aquel joven Cui que nunca había manchado sus dedos con trabajo rudo,
is now willing and glad to cross
ahora está dispuesto
mountains and hills to collect stones.
a cruzar montañas y valles buscando piedras.
If I can restore my father's map
Si puedo restaurar
of mineral deposits
el mapa de minerales de mi padre
and help you produce caltrop fireballs,
y ayudarte a fabricar la granada de fuego,
it'll be counted
será como
as my atonement for the Cui family.
mi expiación por la familia Cui.
If your sister knew this,
Si tu hermana lo supiera,
she would be rather gratified.
estaría orgullosa de ti.
I'm setting out right now.
Me voy ahora mismo.
Just as usual,
Como siempre,
I'll send you letters
si hay noticias,
on any updates via carrier pigeons.
te las enviaré por paloma mensajera.
No need to rush like this.
No es necesario apresurarte tanto.
I know you're eager to get things done.
Sé que tienes prisa.
The military grain canal is being built at full speed.
Las rutas de suministro están en construcción.
Once it's completed,
Una vez terminadas,
the army will head north for battle.
el siguiente paso será la expedición al norte.
There isn't much time left for the production
El tiempo para fabricar la granada de fuego
of caltrop fireballs.
se está acabando.
Keep yourself safe.
Ten cuidado.
The 78th attempt failed.
Intento número setenta y ocho, no funcionó.
Nonetheless...
Sin embargo,
the ore made great purple-red fireworks.
el efecto de los fuegos artificiales rojo-púrpura es excelente.
Suggested usage: fireworks for the Lantern Festival.
Sugiero usarlos para el Festival de las Linternas.
It was not entirely fruitless.
Al menos obtuvimos algo, ¿no?
Cheer up, Nanxing.
Anímate, Nanxing.
This mess is yours to handle now.
Te dejo todo aquí.
To my beloved wife Yaoyao, reading this is like seeing me in person.
Mi querida esposa Yaoyao, al leer esto es como verme.
The first snow arrived in the Northern Border early.
La primera nieve en el Norte llegó temprano.
Fortunately, I didn't let the court down
Por suerte, cumplí con lo que me encargaron.
by eliminating all the bandits in the southwest,
Los bandidos del suroeste han sido eliminados.
and thus clearing a lurking peril for Ye.
Ye ya no tiene problemas internos.
I am deeply relieved.
Me alegra mucho.
However, the grain canal is not yet finished.
Pero las rutas de suministro aún no están listas,
I'm afraid I can't spend the New Year with you.
temo no poder pasar el Año Nuevo contigo.
In the next spring,
En la próxima primavera,
I will be waiting in the Northern Border for your return.
te esperaré en el Norte.
People who don't know better would think
Quien no lo sepa pensaría
it's been ages since Your Ladyship and His Highness last met.
que el heredero y usted llevan mucho tiempo sin verse.
Didn't His Highness take a detour
¿Acaso el heredero
to this place to visit Your Ladyship
no pasó por aquí a propósito para verla a usted
before setting out to fight the bandits?
antes de ir a la campaña contra los bandidos?
That was already three months ago.
Eso fue hace tres meses ya.
Besides, last time we met,
Además, la última vez que nos vimos,
I barely got the time to say much to him.
ni siquiera tuve tiempo de decirle nada.
Fine, if you say so.
Sí, sí, sí.
My Lady, over the past two years, you've traveled everywhere
Señorita, ha recorrido todo Ye en estos dos años
in Ye, looking for proper ore to make caltrop fireballs.
buscando los minerales para fabricar la granada de fuego,
You've also designed many farming tools
y también ha diseñado tantas herramientas agrícolas,
and opened branches of the Miraculous Craft nationwide.
abriendo la Tienda Maravillosa por todo Ye.
When there are harvests,
Cuando llegue la época de cosecha abundante,
the credit will all go to you.
todo es mérito será suyo, señorita.
My Lady,
Señorita,
where is our next destination?
¿a dónde vamos ahora?
Tian Quan should've paid the debt three days ago,
Ya han pasado más de tres días desde la fecha de pago.
yet he has not come.
Tian Quan aún no ha venido.
He's not trying to renege on it, is he?
¿No querrá no pagar?
Everyone's saying that my husband Tian Quan
Se dice que Tian Quan
embezzled the funds for building the grain canal.
se apropió del dinero para construir la ruta de suministros.
He couldn't take it
Él no pudo soportarlo
and hanged himself.
y se ahorcó.
What grain canal?
¿Qué ruta de suministros?
The canal for transporting grain and forage to the Northern Border.
La ruta para llevar provisiones al Norte.
My Lady,
Señorita,
now that Tian Quan is dead,
si Tian Quan ha muerto,
I'm afraid we won't be able to get our money back.
me temo que no recuperaremos nuestro dinero.
Miss, if you're here to collect the debt,
Señorita, si viene a cobrar la deuda,
all I can offer is my worthless life.
solo me queda mi vida.
If you want it, miss,
Si la quiere, señorita,
then just take it.
tómela.
What exactly happened?
¿Qué pasó exactamente?
Weren't all the tenant farmers and artisans of the village
¿No fueron reclutados todos los campesinos y artesanos
on the east conscripted to build the grain canal?
de la aldea del este para construir la ruta de suministros?
Why would there be embazzlement?
¿Cómo es que hubo corrupción?
The officials were pressing hard,
Las autoridades nos presionaban mucho.
so my husband led everyone
Mi esposo trabajó con todos
to work day and night non-stop.
día y noche.
The job was finally done.
Por fin terminaron,
Yet the higher-ups said the funds for building the canal hadn't arrived.
pero luego nos dijeron que el pago tendría que esperar.
But who doesn't have their hopes pinned on this money for the New Year?
Todos esperábamos ese dinero para pasar el Año Nuevo.
Then why did people accuse
¿Y entonces por qué dicen que
your husband of embezzling the canal construction funds?
tu esposo se robó el dinero?
I swear to heaven that he didn't!
¡Por el cielo!
My husband once
Ese día,
went to the local government to demand justice.
mi esposo fue a reclamar a la oficina del gobierno
Not only did he fail to get a single coin,
y no solo no le dieron ni un céntimo,
but he was beaten and sent back.
sino que lo golpearon y lo echaron.
Besides...
Pero...
Besides what?
¿Pero qué?
Besides, after my husband came home,
Cuando volvió mi esposo,
he kept cursing Lord Li, the magistrate,
no paraba de maldecir al magistrado Li,
declaring him to be
diciendo que es un corrupto
a heinous corrupt official who only knows to flatter his superiors.
que solo sabe adular a los superiores.
Go home with your child.
Lleva al niño a casa.
If there is indeed an injustice,
Si hay una injusticia,
the Young Lady will seek redress for everyone.
nuestra señorita hará justicia por todos.
Thank you, miss.
Gracias, señorita.
My Lady.
Señorita,
I made inquiries at the local government.
fui a la oficina del condado a investigar.
County Magistrate Li Geng left three days ago
El magistrado Li Geng se fue hace tres días
for Jiankang,
a Jiankang.
as the triennial official evaluation
La evaluación trienal de funcionarios
is about to commence.
está por comenzar.
He is likely taking advantage of the New Year
Li Geng debe estar aprovechando el Año Nuevo
to bribe his way
para hacer contactos, sobornar
up and down the ranks.
y hacer sus conexiones.
What an outrage.
¡Qué descaro!
Nanxing.
Nanxing.
Yes.
Presente.
Pack up our stuff.
Empaca las cosas
We are going back to Jiankang.
y regresamos a Jiankang.
Got it.
Sí.
Little trinkets for sale!
¡Pequeñas baratijas!
Trinkets for sale!
¡Baratijas!
Come and take a look!
¡Vengan a ver!
It's been two years.
Dos años sin volver,
Jiankang has become more bustling than before.
Jiankang está más animado que antes.
It's said that Prince Qi is very popular with the people.
He oído que el Príncipe Qi es muy querido por el pueblo.
"A dark eagle soars out of Mount Qi,
"El águila negra sale del Monte Qi
bringing in a year of peace."
y trae años de paz".
It's a compliment to Prince Qi
Todo es el elogio para el Príncipe Qi
for his excellence governance.
por su buen gobierno.
I know.
Lo sé.
Everyone
Todos ellos
hopes for peace and prosperity.
esperan que el mundo esté en paz.
Look.
Mira,
Isn't that Li Geng?
¿ese es Li Geng?
Yes, exactly.
Sí, es él.
Let's go.
Vamos.
Bravo! Bravo!
¡Bien, bien!
[County Magistrate, Li Geng]
[Li Geng, magistrado del condado]
I heard that once corrupt officials from all over enter Jiankang,
Dicen que cuando los funcionarios corruptos llegan a Jiankang,
they'd buy a calligraphy painting from Guanhai House
van al Pabellón Guanhai a comprar una pintura,
and give it as a gift.
y luego usan esa pintura para sobornar.
Those who receive paintings will sell them
Los que reciben los sobornos llevan las pinturas
back to Guanhai House for money.
de vuelta al Pabellón Guanhai para cambiarlas por dinero.
It's practically an industry then.
Es todo un negocio.
Look, Li Geng is holding a painting.
Mira, Li Geng lleva una pintura.
It seems he's going to meet the one
Parece que hoy va a ver
manipulating the buying and selling of official posts.
al que maneja la compra y venta de cargos.
Perfect.
Perfecto.
Let's find out the vermin of the court
Veremos a estos gusanos del estado
and root them out altogether.
y los eliminaremos de una vez.
[Xiyue Restaurant]
[Pabellón Xiyue]
Wait.
Espera.
Why did he enter Xiyue Restaurant instead?
¿Por qué va al Pabellón Xiyue?
Come on, let's go get changed.
Vamos, cambiémonos de ropa.
Thereafter, the saying began to spread—
Así surgió el rumor de
"When the Phoenix Heart Tokens appear, peace shall be restored in the world."
"cuando aparezca la llave del corazón del fénix, el mundo se unificará".
Are you from Youzhou?
¿Tú vienes de Youzhou?
I am the magistrate of Pingjiang County,
Soy el magistrado del condado de Pingjiang,
Yueyang Prefecture.
bajo la jurisdicción de Yueyang.
What about you?
¿Y tú?
-I'm from Changping County. -Look.
- El condado de Changping sufrió - Mira,
-There was a locusts disaster last year. -This one's nice.
- una plaga de langostas el año pasado. - esto es bueno.
I even sold my ancestral house to scrape together
Yo vendí la casa de mis antepasados
some silver,
para reunir algo de dinero
hoping to smoothen my way through the triennial evaluation.
y aprovechar la evaluación de tres años para hacer contactos.
Did you not buy a painting?
¿No compraste una pintura?
I heard that without a painting,
Dicen que sin pintura
one doesn't even get to meet the inspector
no puedes ver al evaluador oficial
or the state and county personnel appraisers.
ni a los inspectores, ¿eh?
I bought a painting. I did.
Sí compré, sí compré.
That one is it.
Esa de ahí.
It cost me 5,000 taels of silver.
Me costó cinco mil taels de plata.
Five thousand taels?
¿Cinco mil taels?
No easy task, really.
Qué difícil es.
What kind of painting could cost that much?
¿Qué pintura vale cinco mil?
This is a bribe.
Eso es un soborno.
I made it! I made it!
¡Listo, listo, listo!
The inspector said
El evaluador oficial dijo
I performed extraordinarily in the past three years
que mi desempeño en estos tres años fue excelente,
and that I'd at least get one "Excellent" rating!
al menos me darán una calificación de "superior".
Congratulations!
¡Felicidades, felicidades!
-Congratulations! -Thank you.
- Felicidades. - Muchas gracias.
Magistrate of Pingjiang County, Yueyang Prefecture!
Magistrado del condado de Pingjiang de Yueyang.
It's my turn.
Me toca a mí.
Good luck to you!
¡Buena suerte!
Wish you success!
¡Que todo salga bien!
Greetings, Inspector.
Saludos, señor evaluador oficial.
I am the Magistrate of Pingjiang County, Yueyang Prefecture.
Soy el magistrado del condado de Pingjiang de Yueyang.
Pingjiang County had a good harvest last year.
El condado de Pingjiang tuvo un año de buena cosecha.
How come you only offer 12,000 taels?
¿Cómo es que solo traes doce mil taels?
How dare he ask for more.
¿Y todavía le parece poco?
Speak up.
Dime,
What rating would you like me to give you?
¿qué calificación quieres que te dé?
If I ask for an "Excellent" in all three categories...
Si quiero obtener tres calificaciones superiores...
That will take more than this painting of Snow on Spring River.
Esta pintura Nieve primaveral en el río no sería suficiente.
Xiao Wuyi?
¿Xiao Wuyi?
Why is it you?
¿Cómo es que eres tú?
It should be me asking you that.
Yo también quería preguntarte,
Why are you messing things up here?
¿qué haces aquí causando problemas?
Didn't you tell me
¿No me dijiste que
you were off to fight bandits?
te ibas a combatir a los bandidos?
How are you an inspector...
¿Cómo es que ahora eres evaluador...?
So you're the one taking bribes through paintings?
¿Eres el que recibe sobornos de pinturas?
Why do you need so many of them?
¿Para qué quieres tantas pinturas?
Xiao Wuyi, you...
Xiao Wuyi, tú...
Hey, what did you just do?
Oye, ¿qué haces?
Why did you smash that cup?
¿Por qué rompes la taza?
The second floor is secured.
El segundo piso ya está bajo control.
Wuyi, why did you...
Wuyi, ¿por qué...?
Jiayu?
¿Jiayu?
What are you doing here?
¿Qué haces aquí?
Your Highness.
Su Alteza.
Greet him again.
No, otra vez.
Father.
Padre.
That's is more like it.
Así está mejor.
W-What does this stroke mean?
Esta... esta marca, ¿qué significa?
It means two copies,
Dos copias.
referring to two identical
Dos copias iguales
calligraphic pieces of Liu Jiang Tie.
de la Caligrafía del río Liujiang.
Li Geng is pretty rich then.
Este Li Geng tiene bastante dinero.
The calculation's done.
Ya terminé de contar.
Altogether 47 officials from various areas
Han llegado a la capital un total
came to the capital city.
de 47 funcionarios de todas las regiones.
The money paid as bribes under the guise of art works
Los sobornos en pinturas
is about 170,000 taels.
suman aproximadamente 170 mil taels.
How dare they.
Muy bien.
When I asked them to build the canal,
Les pido que me construyan canales
they complained about being poor all the time.
y todos los días se quejan de que no tienen dinero.
But they sent 170,000-tael-worth gifts without hassle
Pero para sobornar en las evaluaciones,
for the performance evaluation.
sacan 170 mil taels sin problemas.
Some officials they are.
Qué bien.
What do you plan to do with them?
¿Qué piensas hacer?
Among these people,
Entre estas personas,
many are from humble origins and were promoted
muchas son de origen humilde que ascendieron
by you after the reform began.
después de tu reforma.
Send them all to the Ministry of Justice.
Envíalos a todos al Tribunal de Justicia.
Wuyi, absolutely clear water is no habitat for fish.
Wuyi, en el agua demasiado limpia no hay peces.
This is officialdom,
Esto es política,
not a military camp.
no el ejército.
The Beifu Reform has been going smoothly over these two years.
En estos dos años, la reforma de Beifu ha avanzado bien,
It is first due to the concession of noble families,
en parte por el compromiso de las familias nobles,
and second to these officials from humble origins,
y en parte porque estos funcionarios de origen humilde
who have done a lot of real work for you.
te han hecho muchos favores.
If you have all of them punished,
Si los castigas a todos,
I'm afraid others will be disheartened.
se desanimarán.
You'd hate to be an isolated minister, right?
¿Quieres ser un funcionario solitario?
Then investigate each of them.
Investiga uno por uno.
Those who sold their ancestral houses will be exempted.
Los que vendieron sus propias casas ancestrales no cuentan.
Give the money back to them and chase them away.
Que devuelvan el dinero y se larguen.
Those who are found to have imposed exorbitant taxes,
Los que hayan cobrado impuestos ilegales,
embezzled disaster relief funds,
desviado fondos de ayuda
or fraudulently claimed canal building funds
o reclamado dinero de construcción de canales fraudulentamente,
will have to cough up
que devuelvan
every tael of silver they took,
todo el dinero que robaron
and be sent to the Ministry of Justice.
y luego envíenlos al Tribunal de Justicia.
All illicit gains must be confiscated.
El dinero incautado irá a las arcas públicas.
The grain canal building is short of funds.
La ruta de suministros necesita dinero.
If we wait for the court to allocate funds,
Si esperamos a que la corte asigne fondos,
I'm afraid the canal can't be finished
el canal no se terminará
even in the next year.
hasta el año que viene.
Got it.
Sí, señor.
Hold on!
Espera.
Don't forget about that guy named Li Geng.
Y ese tal Li Geng,
It was he who embezzled
él fue quien
the pay for the workers building the canal.
se robó el dinero de la construcción de los canales,
To add to that,
y además tiene
he caused a man's death.
una vida en su conciencia.
You must not let him get away.
No lo dejes escapar.
I misinterpreted your action.
Te malinterpreté.
My apologies.
Lo siento.
I thought you were that corrupt inspector,
Pensé que eras el corrupto.
but it turned out you were on a sting operation.
No sabía que estabas tendiendo una trampa.
Well, you see...
Mira...
I'm so tired
El viaje de hoy
from that lengthy journey today.
ha sido muy agotador,
I also helped catch many corrupt officials.
y además atrapé a muchos corruptos.
It's getting late.
Ya está oscureciendo.
Father,
Padre,
I'd like to go and get some rest now.
hoy me retiraré a descansar primero.
I will come greet you again tomorrow.
Mañana vendré a saludarlo.
Xie Jiayu, stop running!
¡Xie Jiayu, no huyas!
You didn't even recognize the accounting symbols just now.
Hace un momento ni siquiera reconociste los símbolos de contabilidad.
How could you?
¿Qué significa eso?
Come back here!
¡Regresa aquí!
Xie Jiayu!
¡Xie Jiayu!
Xie Jiayu,
Xie Jiayu,
I sent over so much pear blossom candy
te envié tantos pasteles de pera
so as to encourage you to practice hard.
para que practicaras bien tus cuentas,
But you actually tricked me by having Nanxing do all the accounting.
pero tú le pediste a Nanxing que hiciera los cálculos por ti para engañarme.
At this rate,
Si sigues así,
how are you going to handle
¿cómo vas a administrar las cuentas
the finances of Prince Jing'an's Mansion in the future?
de la Mansión del Rey Jing'an en el futuro?
Yuanji,
Yuanji,
Nanxing's here to help, isn't she?
¿no está Nanxing para eso?
All Nanxing can do is render some help.
Nanxing solo puede ayudarte.
You must learn how to do the calculation yourself.
Primero debes aprender a hacerlo tú misma.
Well, you're also
Pero, ¿no
here to help, aren't you, Yuanji?
estás tú también, Yuanji?
Every year I propose to hand the accounts over to you,
Todos los años digo que te pasaré las cuentas
yet you always make excuses to dodge it.
y todos los años te escaqueas.
When the next year begins,
Cuando llegue el año nuevo,
I'll have to return to Yuxi Prefecture with the He family.
tendré que regresar a Yuxi con el clan He.
Let's see how long you can keep avoiding it.
Veamos hasta cuándo puedes seguir evitándolo.
Yuanji,
Yuanji,
could you please stay?
¿no puedes quedarte?
So you did all that on purpose?
¿Lo hiciste a propósito?
I...
Yo...
Silly girl,
Tontita.
I also yearn to live my own life.
Yo también quiero vivir mi propia vida.
Now, things in the He family have settled down.
Ahora que la familia He está estabilizada,
I finally get a chance to go see the outside world
por fin puedo salir a conocer el mundo
just like you do.
como tú.
Being constrained by the He family first,
Antes fui de los He,
and then the Xiao family,
luego de los Xiao.
I was never myself.
Nunca fui yo misma.
This time,
Esta vez,
I'd like to be my real self for once.
quiero ser He Yuanji.
Well...
Entonces,
Is Mr. Liu going with you?
¿el señor Liu te acompañará?
Actually,
En realidad,
I think Anmin is better.
prefiero a Xiao Yao.
If you chose him,
Si eliges a Xiao Yao,
then we can
entonces
spend every day together in the future.
podremos estar juntas todos los días.
You're hoping for that
¿Y así
so you can avoid learning accounting forever, right?
nunca tendrías que aprender a hacer cuentas?
Why does constant parting
¿Por qué crecer
have to be part of growing up?
significa separarse siempre?
Rest assured, Yuanji.
No te preocupes, Yuanji.
I'll try my best to learn.
Voy a estudiar bien.
The Eastern Palace summons the Heir and Lady Xie.
El Palacio Oriental convoca al heredero y a usted, señorita.
His Highness is waiting now.
El heredero ya está esperando.
The Eastern Palace learned of your return so soon?
¿El Palacio Oriental se enteró tan rápido de tu regreso?
We've parted for two years.
Dos años sin vernos,
Why never say a word about your return?
¿ni siquiera me avisaron al volver?
[Chief Eunuch of the Eastern Palace, Feng An]
[Feng An, eunuco del Palacio Oriental]
You just had to make me send an invitation to Prince Jing'an's Mansion.
¿Tengo que ir a la Mansión del Rey Jing'an a buscarlos?
See all those memorials behind me?
¿Ves esos memoriales detrás de mí?
You're being impeached in every one.
Todos son contra ti,
The officials from poor families, who were promoted by you,
acusando a los funcionarios de origen humilde que promoviste
are said to have bribed the inspector.
de sobornar a los evaluadores.
You knew that long ago, didn't you?
¿No lo sabías ya?
The officials involved were arrested in Xiyue Restaurant.
Ya arrestaron a la gente en el Pabellón Xiyue.
Or you couldn't have summoned us so soon, right?
Si no, ¿por qué nos convocarías tan rápido?
What was the amount of bribery?
¿Cuánta plata enviaron?
Every item added up to 170,000 taels of silver.
En total, 170 mil taels.
I directed it all to build the grain canal.
Los he desviado para construir la ruta de suministros.
The Department of State Affairs is too slow with funding.
El Ministerio de Asuntos de Estado tarda mucho en aprobar los fondos,
And it takes you a lot of work to deal with the ministries.
y negociar con cada departamento es un fastidio para ti.
I'm just helping you
Te estoy ayudando
warn the newly promoted officials
a darles una lección a los recién promovidos de origen humilde,
from humble origins to stay on the right path.
para que pongan su esfuerzo en lo que deben.
As long as you don't fear offending anyone.
Mientras no temas ofender a nadie, está bien.
Oh right.
Por cierto,
The New Year is approaching.
pronto será el Año Nuevo.
Do you need to hurry back to the Northern Border?
¿Tienes prisa por volver al Norte?
Any orders from Your Highness?
¿Qué órdenes tienes, Su Alteza?
What can I possibly order you to do?
¿Qué puedo ordenarte?
I heard your father came back, didn't he?
Es que he oído que tu padre ha vuelto.
Since everyone is around now,
Justo estamos todos aquí,
we can celebrate the New Year together.
podemos pasar el Año Nuevo juntos.
Right, Jiayu?
¿Verdad, Jiayu?
Mao, is that soft armor?
Mao, ¿es una cota de malla fina?
Premium materials.
De buena calidad
Exquisite workmanship.
y fina hechura.
It's really well made.
Está muy bien hecha.
Actually,
En realidad,
it's my gift to you for your conferment.
es el regalo que quería darte por tu nombramiento.
Chan.
Chan.
Chan?
¿Chan?
To be honest,
Para ser sincero,
I've taken Chan as a concubine of mine.
ya nombré a Chan como concubina del palacio.
Why did no one tell me I was to be conferred on
¿Nombrar a la consorte?
the title of Heir's Consort?
¿Cómo no lo sabía yo?
Wuyi already divorced Lady He.
Wuyi ya se divorció de la señorita He.
How can the dignified heir of Prince Jing'an
El heredero de la Mansión del Rey Jing'an
not have a consort?
no puede estar sin consorte.
So, I directly petitioned His Majesty
Así que, sin consultarles,
before asking for your approval
le pedí al emperador
to confer on Jiayu the title of Heir's Consort.
que nombrara a Jiayu como consorte.
His Majesty even specially ordered a seal
Su Majestad encargó a la Fábrica Imperial
and a certificate to be made
que hiciera un sello
by the Imperial Works Department.
y el decreto.
I haven't even brought it up yet,
Ni siquiera tuve tiempo de mencionarlo.
and you're already more eager than I am.
Tienes más prisa que yo.
After the New Year,
Después de que pase el Año Nuevo,
I will make sure there is
les organizaré
a grand conferment ceremony for you two.
una gran ceremonia de investidura.
Yaoyao,
Yaoyao,
the mechanical arts you love studying do not
te gusta estudiar esos mecanismos.
bring less danger than battle does.
A veces eso es más peligroso que el campo de batalla.
As you get in and out of the workshop,
Cuando vayas a la forja,
wearing this armor
ponte esta cota,
can provide some protection.
te protegerá un poco.
There's also a calligraphic work for you two.
Junto con esta caligrafía que les regalo,
[May you a lifetime of happiness]
[Cien años de feliz unión]
Consider it
considérenlo
a wedding gift from me to you.
mi regalo de bodas para ustedes.
The Heir Consort's conferment ceremony...
La investidura de la consorte del heredero.
It's a serious matter.
Es algo tan importante.
Mao should've discussed with us earlier.
Mao ni siquiera lo consultó antes.
Also, little did I expect
Pero no esperaba
Chan to be taken as a royal concubine.
que Chan se convirtiera en concubina del palacio.
It didn't occur to me either.
Yo tampoco lo esperaba.
Actually, the conferment ceremony
En realidad, la ceremonia de investidura
isn't really that big a deal, is it?
no es tan importante, ¿verdad?
How is it not a big deal?
¿Cómo que no es importante?
The entire process of it is even
Todo el proceso
more complicated than a wedding's.
es más complicado que una boda.
I thought you'd be delighted.
Pensé que estarías feliz.
Of course I'm delighted.
Claro que estoy feliz,
It's just a bit too sudden.
pero fue muy repentino.
Just some rituals performed at home.
Es una ceremonia familiar,
They're hardly as complicated as you think.
no es tan complicada como crees.
What surprised me
No esperaba que
was that Yizhi had a seal newly made and asked
Yizhi mandara a hacer un nuevo sello
the Inner Court's Rites Directorate to prepare for the ceremony.
y ordenara a la Oficina de Ceremonias de la corte organizar la ceremonia.
It's actually good.
Así está bien.
I promised your mother
Le prometí a tu madre
not to drag you into the mess I'm in.
que no te involucraría en mis problemas.
I've broken my word.
Ya he roto mi promesa.
Now that it's all inevitable,
Ya que no se puede evitar,
I must give you the strongest armor.
debo darte la mejor armadura.
With that seal and the official conferment,
Con la investidura formal y el sello,
everything in Prince Jing'an's Mansion
a partir de ahora podrás disponer de todo
will be at your command from now on.
en la Mansión del Rey Jing'an.
No one can hurt you.
Nadie podrá hacerte daño.
In Prince Jing'an's Mansion, would anyone give me
En la Mansión del Rey Jing'an, aparte de ti,
a hard time except you?
¿alguien me hizo daño?
No, I suppose.
Parece que no.
Xiao Wuyi,
Xiao Wuyi,
will you head north for battle soon?
¿vas a empezar la expedición al norte pronto?
I'm sick of receiving letters from home
He recibido cartas tuyas durante dos años
for the past two years.
y ya estoy harto de leerlas.
I want to go to Beifu with you.
Quiero ir contigo a Beifu.
My face hurts from all that smiling.
Me duele la cara de tanto reír.
You think the guests were too many?
¿Esto te parece mucho?
They were just a few soldiers' families, coming to offer New Year's greetings.
Solo son algunas familias de los soldados que vinieron a saludar.
It is finally over.
Por fin se fueron.
I have serious business to attend to.
Tengo asuntos importantes que hacer.
What serious business?
¿Qué asuntos importantes tienes?
Xiao Wuyi agreed to let me join the army.
Xiao Wuyi aceptó que lo acompañe con el ejército.
Now, I am Beifu Army's ordinance supervisor.
Seré la supervisora de armamento del ejército de Beifu.
Finally,
Ahora
my skills are needed somewhere.
mis habilidades por fin tendrán donde aplicarse.
You're joining the army?
¿Vas a ir con el ejército?
Then what about the household affairs?
¿Y qué pasa con los asuntos de la mansión?
My Lady,
Señorita,
I have to manage the Miraculous Craft for you.
todavía tengo que encargarme de la Tienda Mano Maravillosa.
Dear Nanxing, don't be modest.
Vamos, Nanxing, no seas tan modesta.
Thanks to you and Jing Lan, the Miraculous Craft
La Tienda Mano Maravillosa se ha extendido por todo Ye
could open branches
en tan poco tiempo
all over Ye within such a short time.
gracias a ti y a Jinglan.
Someone talented like you is not to be wasted.
Un talento como el tuyo no puede desperdiciarse.
Yuanji,
Yuanji,
I'm not being a lazybones.
esto no se llama holgazanear,
I'm just assigning the right person to the right position.
esto se llama saber asignar a las personas correctas.
You can always come up with excuses.
Siempre tienes una respuesta.
This won't do.
No,
I'm just a servant.
yo solo soy una sirvienta.
So what if you are a servant?
¿Y qué importa ser sirvienta?
Years ago,
Yo antes
I was just a butcher's daughter.
solo era hija de un carnicero,
But now,
y ahora
I'm a Princess, aren't I?
soy la reina de esta mansión, ¿no?
Mother.
Madre.
Now that the Heir's Consort thinks highly of you,
La consorte te valora,
just do your job well.
solo tienes que hacer bien tu trabajo.
I swear I will live up to
No defraudaré la confianza de la reina
Your Highnesses' trust.
ni la de la consorte.
Mother, you don't think I'm just messing around?
Madre, ¿no crees que estoy haciendo locuras?
Yuanji loves studying historical texts.
A Yuanji le encanta estudiar historia,
Ruisheng excels at medicine.
Ruisheng es buena en medicina,
You like mechanics.
a ti te gustan los mecanismos,
Yan Yue practices martial arts.
Yan Yue sabe artes marciales,
Nanxing is good at operating business.
Nanxing entiende de negocios.
As for me, I enjoy feeding chickens
Yo, pues, me gusta alimentar gallinas
and raising ducks.
y criar patos.
We all have things
Todas tenemos
we'd like to do.
lo que nos gusta hacer.
Isn't it nice to leverage our own strengths?
¿No es bueno que cada una use sus talentos?
Let's go have
Vamos, vamos.
the New Year's Eve dinner together.
Vamos a cenar juntas para celebrar el Año Nuevo.
Sure.
Bien.
Let's go.
Vamos, vamos.
Xiao Ziqi, sit tight!
Xiao Ziqi, siéntate bien.
I was out practicing medicine all year
He estado todo el año fuera ejerciendo la medicina
and couldn't discipline you.
y no he podido controlarte, ¿eh?
So you started causing trouble here and there.
¿Te has pasado el año haciendo travesuras?
Do you want to memorize the acupoint chart again?
¿Otra vez quieres memorizar los puntos de acupuntura?
Auntie,
Tía,
help me.
auxilio.
Alright, Sister.
Ya, Ruisheng,
Ziqi says he got the message.
Ziqi dice que ya lo sabe.
Now, you spoil him
Ahora
even more than Yuanji does.
lo consientes más que Yuanji.
Someday,
Mañana mismo
I'll send you to a school in the mountains.
te envío a una escuela en la montaña,
The kind where you can't leave until ten years later.
y no saldrás en diez años.
Come here!
Ven acá.
Behave.
No hagas tonterías.
Father, Mother,
Padre, madre,
I'm sorry to be late.
he llegado tarde.
Almost missed the New Year's Eve dinner.
Casi me pierdo la cena de Año Nuevo.
Didn't you say you were busy with the grain canal
¿No dijiste que tenías mucho trabajo en la ruta de suministros
and couldn't come back for the dinner?
y que no volverías este año?
I heard there would be a conferment ceremony.
Me enteré de que habría una ceremonia de investidura,
Wuyi and Jiayu are both back.
y que Wuyi y mi cuñada volvían.
As their elder brother,
Como hermano mayor,
how could I not come home?
¿cómo podría no volver?
We are all family.
Somos familia,
No need for formalities.
no hay tantas formalidades.
Mother,
Madre,
I noticed last time that your neck warmer was broken.
la última vez vi que tu collar estaba roto,
So I asked a merchant from the Western Regions
le pedí a un comerciante de la Región Occidental
to buy a new one.
que me trajera uno nuevo.
Please try it on, Mother.
Pruébalo, madre.
Bring it to me, quick.
Rápido, rápido.
How thoughtful of you, Yao.
Yao, eres muy atento.
Take a seat already.
Siéntate, siéntate.
Brother.
Yao.
Yuanji.
Yuanji.
This year, the Xiao family
Este año es el año
is the most complete than ever.
con más familiares reunidos en la familia Xiao.
Come on,
Vamos,
let's celebrate the New Year together.
todos juntos. ¡Feliz Año Nuevo!
May we have happiness, longevity, and health.
¡Salud y larga vida!
Happy New Year.
¡Feliz Año Nuevo!
Wuyi knows you loves sweet wine, Mother,
Madre, Wuyi sabe que a usted le encanta el vino dulce,
so he wrote to me early on,
así que en su carta me pidió
telling me to prepare some good wine
que cuando las uvas estuvieran maduras,
upon the harvest of grapes,
preparara este vino especial
and make sure it is presented to you on the New Year.
para regalárselo en Año Nuevo.
How considerate of our children.
Qué atentos son, hijos.
Good!
¡Bien!
Back in the day, your mother here
En sus tiempos, su madre
was a famous wine enthusiast.
era una famosa bebedora.
Tonight,
Entonces, esta noche
let's have many a drink
la acompañaremos
with your mother!
a beber bien,
How about that?
¿de acuerdo?
Sure.
De acuerdo.
I'd like to enjoy such fine wine
Que sea como acompañar a mi madre
with Mother.
a disfrutar de este vino.
Dishes bestowed by the Eastern Palace!
El Palacio Oriental envía manjares.
Everyone in Prince Jing'an's Mansion, receive the dishes and the edict!
Todos en la Mansión del Rey Jing'an, reciban el obsequio y el edicto.
By decree of the Eastern Palace,
Edicto del Palacio Oriental.
as the year renews
El año nuevo comienza,
and a new dawn breaks,
la fiesta del primer día se inaugura.
considering your relentless efforts day and night,
Considerando su valor en la batalla contra los bandidos
I find your loyalty and diligence commendable.
y su constante diligencia y lealtad,
Today, I bestow upon you a feast of delicacies,
hoy les concedo un banquete de ocho delicias
named "National Unity
llamado "Corazones unidos bajo el cielo,
and Family Reunion."
familia reunida".
You shall understand the regard I bear for you,
Que comprendan mi afecto por ustedes
strive more earnestly in public causes,
y se esfuercen más.
and remain of one mind with me, as ruler and ministers.
Que el soberano y súbditos sean unidos en corazón.
As His Highness commands.
Yo, su servidor, recibo el edicto.
Come on in.
Vamos, vamos.
Let's continue to drink.
Sigamos bebiendo.
Come on.
Vamos.
The man in black there,
Oye, el de negro,
won't you come eat with us?
¿de verdad no vas a comer con nosotros?
It's New Year's Eve dinner.
Es la cena de Año Nuevo.
Yes. Mr. Ye Xing,
Así es, Ye Xing,
Her Ladyship said
nuestra señorita dijo
you should have New Year's Eve dinner with us.
que cenes con nosotros.
Leave him alone.
Déjalo,
As a royal Shadow Envoy,
es un Enviado de la Sombra Imperial,
he will by no means forget the rules.
las reglas están grabadas en sus huesos.
You drunk kitten,
Borrachita,
it's time to go home.
es hora de volver a casa.
Why did you come to the horse ranch?
¿Qué haces en el picadero?
When Anmin gave a neck warmer to Mother,
¿Por qué cuando tu hermano mayor le regaló un collar a madre,
why did you hide yours?
tú escondiste el tuyo?
If I remember correctly,
Si no recuerdo mal,
that was made with the red fox
ese lo hiciste
you hunted on your own, right?
con piel del zorro rojo que cazaste, ¿verdad?
♪ One glance from near stirs my heart ♪
♪ Un pensamiento, una crisis del corazón, a un paso, una mirada ♪
Xiao Wuyi, this is no good.
Xiao Wuyi, eso está mal,
Really no good.
muy mal.
♪ This fleeting moment ♪
♪ En este momento ♪
Even if others give her a hundred neck warmers,
Aunque le regalen cien,
the one presented by you still has its special meaning.
el que das tú representa tu corazón.
♪ Tugs the threads woven by fate ♪
♪ Tirando de los hilos del destino ♪
Just because someone else sent her a neck warmer
No es porque otros hayan regalado algo,
didn't mean you shouldn't give her one.
entonces tú no puedes regalar.
Do you hear me?
¿Me escuchaste?
♪ Bound tight evermore ♪
♪ Están conectados ♪
♪ Sharing all the years together ♪
♪ Recorriendo juntos los años ♪
Alright.
Bien.
♪ Peace I find nowhere but by your side ♪
♪ Solo a tu lado encuentro la paz ♪
I got it.
Lo sé.
♪ Bear witness with our souls ♪
♪ Con el alma como espejo ♪
Xiao Wuyi,
Xiao Wuyi,
♪ Fear no partings or wax and wane ♪
♪ No tengo miedo de separarme ♪
you need to learn to ask for things.
tienes que aprender a pedir.
♪ You know my resolve to live and die together ♪
♪ Tú me conoces, si lo decido, vivo y muero contigo ♪
♪ Believe in my persistence that I won't run away ♪
♪ Confía en mi determinación de no huir ♪
♪ You know me, I'm willing to be with you till the end ♪
♪ Tú me conoces, dispuesto a estar a tu lado hasta el último aliento ♪
♪ Burn the fire in my heart ♪
♪ hasta consumir el fuego de mi corazón ♪
♪ Sincere hearts remain as of old ♪
♪ Con la misma sinceridad de siempre ♪